Finding Aid to the Alison Bechdel papers SSC.MS.00633
Sophia Smith Collection
Alison Bechdel papers
1980-2017
Sophia Smith Collection
Bechdel, Alison, 1960-
SSC.MS.00633
30.75 linear feet (41 boxes)
This collection is comprised of materials related to works created by Alison Bechdel. It includes business correspondence, character and topic development files, manuscript edits, press interviews, reviews, press releases, and a broad range of texts, sketches, and notes that formed the basis for Bechdel's work from the mid-1980s through the early 2000s.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use with following restrictions on access:
Boxes 7-20 of accession 2008-S-104 must be used with great care; researchers may not disrupt the order of materials.
Accruals
Periodic additions to collection are expected.
Arrangement
This collection has not yet been processed, so is arranged by accession.
Biographical / Historical
Alison Bechdel was born in Lock Haven, Pennsylvania to Bruce Allen Bechdel--high school English teacher, antiques dealer, and funeral director--and Helen Fontana Bechdel--high school English teacher and amateur actress. Her family also owned and operated a funeral home, dubbed the Fun Home by Bechdel and her two brothers.
Bechdel earned her A.A. in 1979 from Simon's Rock Early College (now Simon's Rock of Bard College) and her B.A. from Oberlin College in 1981. She applied to many art schools but was rejected. She worked in various publishing industry office jobs in New York City from 1981 to 1985, and as a production writer for Equal Time in Minneapolis, MN from 1986 to 1990. According to the autobiographical The Indelible Alison Bechdel, she began "Dykes to Watch Out For" (DTWOF) as a single drawing labeled: "Marianne, dissatisfied with the morning brew: Dykes to Watch Out For, plate no. 27." An acquaintance recommended she send her work to Womannews newspaper, which began publishing the strip regularly beginning with the July-August 1983 issue. After a year, other outlets began running the strip, and it was syndicated in 1985.
In 1988, Bechdel began a short-lived, page-length strip about the staff of a queer newspaper, titled Servants to the Cause, for The Advocate newspaper. The success of DTWOF allowed Bechdel to quit her day job in 1990 to work on the strip full-time. Bechdel has written and drawn autobiographical strips, has done illustrations for magazines and websites, and has written numerous books, including Dykes to Watch Out For (1986), More Dykes to Watch Out For (1988), New Improved! Dykes to Watch Out For (1990), Unnatural Dykes to Watch Out For (1995), Hot, Throbbing Dykes to Watch Out For (1997), The Indelible Alison Bechdel: Confessions, Comix and Miscellaneous Dykes to Watch Out For (1998), Dykes and Sundry Other Carbon-based Life-Forms to Watch Out For (2003), Invasion of the Dykes to Watch Out For (2005), Fun Home: A Family Tragicomic (2006), and The Essential Dykes to Watch Out For (2008). Four of Bechdel's books have won Lamba Literary Awards for humor, and The Indelible Alison Bechdel won a Lambda Literary Award in the biography/autobiography category. In February 2004, Bechdel married her partner since 1992, Amy Rubin, in a civil ceremony in San Francisco; they separated in 2006.
Other Finding Aids
This online finding aid currently provides detailed description of only the most recent additions to this collection. Additional materials are described in unpublished lists that can be sent to you upon request by contacting specialcollections@smith.edu
Scope and Contents
The Alison Bechdel papers document the illustrative and written works created by Alison Bechdel. It includes business correspondence for Stationery Flux (S.F.), the business used for Dykes to Watch Out For merchandise, correspondence and royalty information from publishers, character and topic development files, manuscript edits, news clippings, press interviews, reviews, press releases, and a broad range of texts, sketches, and notes that formed the basis for Bechdel's work from the mid-1980s through the early 2010s.
The bulk of the collection documents development files for the syndicated comic strip Dykes to Watch Out For and Servants to the Cause are included. Also included are post-syndication/pre-publication edits for Bechdel's book, Dykes to Watch Out For and Fun Home.
Cartoonists--United States--Biography--Sources; Lesbian artists--United States; Lesbianism in art; Lesbianism--United States--Caricatures and cartoons; Lesbian feminism--United States--History--Sources; Lesbians--United States--Biography--Sources; American wit and humor, Pictorial; Bechdel, Alison, 1960-. Dykes to watch out for -- Sources; Cartoons (humorous images); clippings; correspondence; Financial records; Notes; press releases; Publicity; Reviews; Sketches; Drawings; Bechdel, Alison, 1960-; Bechdel, Alison, 1960-
- Alison Bechdel project files, touring files, and correspondence, 2018-S-0084; 4 linear feet (2 record cartons, 3 flat boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes project files, touring information, reader correspondence, collaborations with other artists, large drafts of works, and slides of photographs and comic pages
  - Project files (drawing drafts, photocopies, correspondence with commissioning party), 1980-1994; 70 folders (70 folders) (Box 37)
  - Oversize drawings from project files, 1980-1994; .5 linear feet (1 flat box) (Box 41)
  - Touring files (schedules, brochures, fliers, and speeches), 1988-1994; 45 folders (45 folders) (Box 37)
  - Japan Media Arts Festival information and award, 2012; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 38, Box 39)
  - Cartoonist articles and examples, 1995-2013; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 38)
  - Vancouver Art Gallery exhibition, 2008; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 38)
  - Reader mail (includes souvenirs, gifts, and zines from fans), 2008-2017; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 38, Box 39)
  - News clippings (related to "Fun Home" and Bechdel), 2006-2008; 4 folders (4 folders) (Box 38, Box 39)
  - Publisher correspondence (Firebrand, Nancy Bereano, LPC Group, Karen Shatzkin, Oosterhous, other business correspondence), 1985-2011; 10 folders (10 folders) (Box 38)
  - Written work, 1988-1992; 3 folders (3 folders) (Box 38)
  - Talks given by Bechdel, 1987-1992; 6 folders (6 folders) (Box 38)
  - Workshops, 1991, 1994; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 38)
  - Slides of comic pages, drawings, and photographs, 1992-2002; .5 linear feet (1 flat box, slides stored in two binders) (Box 40)
- Alison Bechdel papers, 2008-S-0104; 13.25 linear feet (20 boxes)
- 2012-S-0062, 7.5 linear feet (8 boxes)
  Multiple drafts of "Fun Home"as well as research files, fan mail, original art work, and financial records.
- 2013-S-0072, 2 linear feet (2 boxes)
- 2015-S-0002, 2.5 linear feet (3 boxes)
- 2015-S-0039, 1 linear feet (1 box)
  Notes, sketches, research materials, and photos for "Fun Home" (2006).